Guide to the Teddie Martin Papers 1920-1931
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Teddie Martin Papers
1920-1931
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 052
Martin, Teddie, b. 1883
0.5 linear feet 1 box
Teddie Martin owned a general store and was a promient citizen of Alberton, Montana. The collection consists of his business and personal correspondence and materials from the Louis Amans estate, of which he was the executor.
Biographical Note
Teddie Martin was born November 16, 1883 on a farm near Preskisle, Aroostook County, Maine, the fourth child of thirteen born to Vital and Ozita (Leveque) Martin. He arrived in Montana as a child in 1886 when his father, who had come to Montana in 1880 and spent two years in Deer Lodge County in the lumber business, brought the family and became a rancher near Choteau, Montana. About 1889, the family moved to Clinton, Missoula County, Montana, where Teddie spent his childhood and early youth on the old home ranch.
At the age of fourteen he left home to work for Western Lumber Company in Lothrop, Montana, where he remained for eight years before moving to Alberton, Montana, and establishing a residence there in 1907. That same year, he acquired a loan from two bankers in Missoula, Montana, and bought a general merchandise store in Alberton which he operated until a fire destroyed it and his home in December 1928. Martin rebuilt both, and the business continued.
A stalwart member of the Republican Party, member of the Methodist Episcopal Church, affiliated with several bodies of the Masonic fraternities, and holding membership in the Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks (BPOE), Fraternal Order of Eagles (FOE), and the Independent Order of Odd Fellows (IOOF), Martin was a leading citizen and merchant in Alberton.
He married Inez Haight July 22, 1905; their marriage brought them one child, Teddie Jr.
The collection consists of his business and personal correspondence and materials from the Louis Amans estate, of which he was the executor. The correspondence concerns supplies and financial affairs of his general store and Martin's connections with fraternal and business organizations. The Louis Amans file documents Martin's attempts to locate suitable care for Mrs. Amans and to settle her financial affairs.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 0.5 linear feet, 1920-1931
Series II: Louis Amans Estate, 1 folder, 1930
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Date and source of acquisition unknown.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Amans, Louis --Estate; Amans, Louis --Family
Alberton (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Community life--Montana --Alberton; Friendly societies -- Montana--Alberton; General stores--Montana --Alberton
Business records -- Montana--Alberton; Estate records--Montana --Alberton; Personal papers--Montana --Alberton
Montana; Labor History; City and Town Life; Women
Civic leaders--Montana --Alberton; Executors and administrators--Montana--Alberton; Merchants--Montana -- Alberton
- Correspondence, 1920-1931; Series I; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contains Martin's business and personal correspondence. Much of it concerns supplies and financial affairs of his general store; his suppliers responded to the fire of 1928 with condolences and adjustments to his usual orders. The correspondence with Montana Power from 1929 contains a petition for the company to supply Alberton residents with electric lights. Some of the letters are personal, and include those sent by a friend from the Montana State Hospital in Warm Springs. There are also letters concerned with Martin's membership in his various fratnernal and business organizations.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1926 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Montana Power, 1929 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, January-February, 1929 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, April-December, 1929 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, January-March, 1930 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence, April-June, 1930 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, July-September, 1930 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Correspondence, October-December, 1930 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
- Louis Amans Estate, 1930; Series II; 1 folder
  This series contains materials related to the Louis Amans Estate, of which Martin was the executor. The death of Amans left his widow, Maud Ammans, in poor health and virtually without assets. The file documents Martin's attempts to locate suitable care for Mrs. Amans and to settle her financial affairs.
  - Louis Amans Estate, 1930 (Box-folder 1/12)